<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>Paul Meng's Blog</title>
    <link href="https://blog.paulme.ng/rss/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://blog.paulme.ng" />
    <id>https://blog.paulme.ng/rss/feed.xml</id>
    <author>
        <name>Paul Meng</name>
        <email>me@paulme.ng</email>
    </author>
    <updated>2021-05-30T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <entry>
    <title>對於投資想法的一些轉變</title>
    <link href="https://blog.paulme.ng/posts/2021-05-30-%E5%B0%8D%E6%96%BC%E6%8A%95%E8%B3%87%E6%83%B3%E6%B3%95%E7%9A%84%E4%B8%80%E4%BA%9B%E8%BD%89%E8%AE%8A.html" />
    <id>https://blog.paulme.ng/posts/2021-05-30-%E5%B0%8D%E6%96%BC%E6%8A%95%E8%B3%87%E6%83%B3%E6%B3%95%E7%9A%84%E4%B8%80%E4%BA%9B%E8%BD%89%E8%AE%8A.html</id>
    <published>2021-05-30T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2021-05-30T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>前陣子看了阿堯跟威宇最新上傳的 youtube 影片關於對於投資的再思考，我也想花時間紀錄一下自己對於投資理解的改變以及手法上的改變。</p>
<p>對於投資跟投機的定義，市場上對於不同人一直有不同的定義。許多人會依照自身經驗，把比較不熟悉跟新生的事物，或是基本面比較模糊的東西就直接定義成投機。對照自己學習的來說，與其因為符號的關係而把事物認定成二元是本末倒置，事實上實際的運作更有可能的是一個光譜。這有點像是李小龍開創的 Mixed Martial Art，把原本各個流派有用的理論結合成現代武術，或是按照實證醫學的講法可能就是結合運動科學跟實驗精神去打造實證武術。我自己的路程由於工程師背景最早其實接觸的是 Quant，但意識到 Quant 基本上是拼機器跟基礎建設的軍備競賽而轉向基本面，對於傳統技術面來說大概已經比不太過經過實證統計的 Quant，大概只有在對手比較弱或散戶組成比較多的市場還顯著有效，記得有看過索羅斯的前交易員說傳統技術面在美股已經不太有效，但也許像是陸股或台股之類散戶組成比較多的地方大概還是有效，只是弱化而已。正由於手法如此多種而自己都多少接觸過，先來說說我自己覺得不同面向的投資定義方式</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>不需要在乎明天市場開不開，而關注商業競爭本身。價值投資人跟或是激進投資人以及 PE 等等大概落於此光譜</li>
<li>在乎市場是否開，但關注於期望值，而在乎市場是否開的長短以及多少主觀判斷來決定了是類似 Event-Driven 投資人，或是像是 cis 類型的瘋狗流，以及是全自動交易的 Quant</li>
<li>造市商，也就是所謂的高頻交易，這幾乎快是市場的基礎建設，比較難說是純粹的投資。</li>
</ol>
<p>這幾種定義反應的是對於這世界理解，自身的限制，能力以及與哲學上的態度。由於你的交易總是會有不如預期的時候，如果你沒有一套自己的哲學跟邏輯論述，在交易不如預期的時候會陷入進退失據的狀態。在最開始的時候雖然我能接受純技術面或 Quant 能夠賺錢，但自己操作的時候是無法接受純技術面去操作的，主要是心理面無法克服。隨著越讀越多，還有實際看到其他人找到市場中暫時 displacaement 的部分去博弈，漸漸反思自己的整體作法而逐漸改變。</p>
<p>能夠調整主要是意識到，其實不只在投資中，我們在生活中經常依賴所謂的技術面來外包我們的判斷給其他人，就算是那些堅稱自己做價值投資的人，我是很難想像他們在生活中不曾因為某些餐廳大排長龍而，或是在新聞中看到比較多次關鍵詞而被影響去吃一些餐廳。現代社會是複雜的而個人時間有限，對於工程師來說就好像是一個複雜的分散式系統一樣，而我們不可能讀完所有的原始碼，而我們也並沒有一個 dashboard 來追蹤經濟這個機器的每一個面向。所以這時候難免會需要依賴於一些看似巫術的指標去逼近，只要逼近得足夠好不妨礙到我們生活就沒必要改變，除非是指標不夠準而需要精進。反應回交易，這就是必須承認我們實在玩 partial information 的遊戲，如何去權衡在自己的主場中玩 full information 的遊戲或是依賴於一些指標去逼近，就依賴於自己的哲學。而我自己是比較傾向於索羅斯定義的反身性以及他老師 Carl Popper 的科學哲學，就算你相信自己在玩 full information 的遊戲，很多事情是只能被証偽的，相信自己在玩 full information 跟使用巫術來選股，哲學上在被証偽之前可能都是被金融市場視為非無效，這該怎麼取捨還是取決於你自己的貝氏機率的 prior，而這個 prior 很可能決定於你出身的時代，你經歷過的事，當這些成為市場參與者的心理共識時，又會進一步改變市場結構。</p>
<p>說到共識，投資是一個尋求共識的過程，而有些方法就是比較容易說服別人。而所謂的別人，就是市場中資金的參與者，這會根據散戶的比率而造成某些現象在不同市場的差異，因為所需說服的人不同。有些研究說歷史上或有價值跟成長投資的風格切換週期，通常成長股表現比較好是在 Big Debt Cycle 裡面的經濟成長週期，而價值表現比較好通常是經濟走出低谷剛進入復甦的階段。我覺得就是市場在不同的階段，市場上的參與者具有說服力的說詞是不同的，在成長週期中，業績成長就是一番兩瞪眼，不需要多聰明都可以明白。而困境反轉是比較有難度的，畢竟原本的氣氛可能是十分悲觀，但只要業績沒有那麼慘，就可以用數據說服市場的參與者。那究竟能不能用一些指標來知道何時會風格切換呢？目前研究應該是覺得沒辦法，所以反應在自己的作法就是類似艾謝克那樣，用總經資訊像是零售，美元強弱，PMI 等等判斷持股水位，跟風格的倉位。總經方面的資訊很難用到實際的交易，但我覺得用來決定配置的資訊還是有些顯著性的，這就好像是玩大亂鬥之中有一些場地的亂入攻擊你必須要避開，這會來決定你整體策略為何。</p>
<p>手法方面，自己對於每種方法適用的情境，還有自己對於不同產業的估值模型也比較純熟，甚至對於 position sizing 從原本的無所是從，也漸漸有自己的因情境改變的手法。</p>
<p>例如這陣子很流行的瘋狗流，雖然我目前還沒看到有嚴謹的定義，就我的理解，比較像是利用基本面或籌碼面或其他經濟的另類指標，抓到起漲點然後去衝浪，並且加大資金 turn-over 來有效幫助資金成長。這看似不是價值投資但其實我覺得也是非常吃操盤人的經驗跟基本面分析主觀判斷的，但差別點在於他更多的是看待投資為期望值打法，承認自己有些許資訊優勢，但在整個波段可能不是資訊最強的，所以會外包很多判斷給籌碼跟資金流向。然後用停損來控制期望值是正的。對於操盤人本身的心理素質要求也是蠻高的。我個人認為適用的主場是像是台股這樣沒有個人資本利得稅，而且半導體，電子股還有傳產是或多或少算是週期較短的地方，畢竟週期股波峰跟底可能會相差到十倍。在美股的話，如果交易人是美國資本利得稅務身分，而美股市場又是期權市場比較發達的地方，改用 Options 的策略來做區間或是波段會是更適合的作法，但風險不對稱還有下檔保護風險的打法我覺得精神上都是類似的，就是建造一個期望值為正的系統，並且讓你心理可以承受的住。</p>
<p>由於知道瘋狗流的作法，對於一般人理解傳統價值投資的一些盲點也有了更深的體會。我覺得傳統價值投資麻煩的一點就是你不知道會不會是價值陷阱，而多數的書裡面對於 position sizing 以及下檔保護等等的著墨並不多，多數的價值投資人都是說並不會停損，好一點的會說會依照新的資訊如果對於原本進場的 thesis 造成實質的改變就會賣掉。而實際去檢視其實說這些話的人多半都是股東會有實際話語權甚至是決策權的，因為實質的權力可以保護下檔。就算沒有控制權，他們可能也是在挑對手比較弱的主場，譬如說是 micro-cap space，對手沒有其他法人的話就可以優先接觸到管理層，因而有資訊優勢，當然壞處就是 micro-cap 的流動性比較不好，在系統性風險發生的時候不是很好逃跑。對於部位不夠大而價值投資做的好的人，我觀察到的幾乎其實都是在做 Value Trading，其實他們賭的並不見得是三年以上的維度，而是幾季甚至是一年為 timeline 的短暫 value displacement，因而要跑的判斷可能比較容易定義。如果是要完全不停損的話，另一種方式就是要等安全邊際夠大的時期左側交易，大概只能等那種十年一次的系統性風險，那就是變成十年一次壓身家。太過分散的話超額報酬又不高，畢竟超額報酬是博弈而來的。 但這又會牽扯到 position sizing 的問題，萬一你錯了怎麼辦？按照 Joel Greenblatt 的訪談時說法，他的 position sizing 原則是他不是看風險報酬比，而是他覺得會輸錢的絕對數值不大的時候他才會放大部位。如果一個 binary event 上檔是十倍但下檔是歸零的時候是不符合壓大的定義的，但這其實跟期望值打法是異曲同工之妙，只是是利用基本面的計算來控制下檔風險，畢竟下檔控制不外乎幾種方法。</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>跑得快，那就要要求流動性。利用停損來控制損失部位。</li>
<li>基本面來看沒什麼系統性風險，或是提升 security 的優先順位買 preferred stock 或 senior bond。</li>
<li>找博弈對手弱的主場，比別人早知道消息。</li>
<li>利用衍生性金融工具，賭不對稱，譬如波動率高的時候賣 put，在下跌趨勢中買 call</li>
</ol>
<p>從書裡描寫的價值投資直接照搬一般個人情況，在艱難時期或是看錯的時候，常常就是賠大錢的時候。</p>
<p>零零總總打了一堆，算是紀錄一些想法的改變。</p>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Pull yourself out of the tarpit</title>
    <link href="https://blog.paulme.ng/posts/2020-02-23-pull-yourself-out-of-the-tarpit.html" />
    <id>https://blog.paulme.ng/posts/2020-02-23-pull-yourself-out-of-the-tarpit.html</id>
    <published>2020-02-23T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2020-02-23T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I had experienced burned-out in the past two years. The symptoms of burned-out could include</p>
<ul>
<li>Don’t want to go to work, questioning yourself continuing doing certain things.</li>
<li>Unmotivated. You used to be into something, maybe travel, then suddenly you stopped enjoying it. It has become your new normal and you need next big in life. You can’t find your purpose.</li>
<li>Feeling stuck in life. You are an analytical personality and you try to break down the problem into pieces but still unable to find out a solution to break out of the status-quo.</li>
</ul>
<p>I explored and came out my own methodology, I have tried it out on my friends seeking my advice and the experiments so far look positive. It’s not for every one, but if you are from similar background as mine, you might find the methodology helpful. My background is:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Analytical personality, with strong belief in Science or the philosophy foundation established by Karl Popper / Thomas Kuhn.</li>
<li>Agnosticism or Atheism, where you don’t lie your belief system on “believing in god” as the first principle and derive that these all difficulties in life are challenges designed from god, and you believe that eventually you would make through this.</li>
</ol>
<p>I noticed that my methodology is very software operational influenced, or could be logically structured like this:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Mitigate the problem. At least stop bleeding.</li>
<li>Analyse the root cause.</li>
<li>Explore and re-establish your logical/belief network (or software)</li>
</ol>
<p>The first step of mitigating the problem is to make sure you are not sick (that could be measured by modern medicine). Not to jump into the topic of Materialism v.s. Spiritualism, we definitely agree that your body would play a role affecting how you think, or if you’re still able to think rationally. Ruling out the possibility of depression etc would be the first step.</p>
<p>After making sure you’re not sick, you could use body hacking to make yourself better.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Start activity that make your body generate Dopamine without too many side effects. Like excercise. You might feel like doing nothing but you have to force yourself to start it from very small, even just walking 10 minutes, and slowly increase the activity. It’s the same way to treat procrastination.</li>
<li>Jam your brain’s attention. Your attention is limited. And when you are down your attention would be focus on negative thoughts and emotions. However, the right way is not to ask yourself not to think about it. That would backfire. The correct way would be doing something jam your full attention bandwidth, so it leaves no space to negative thoughts. That’s how travel to some where you’re unfamiliar would work, because your day-to-day attention would be jammed by new information like “how do I get to the next destination?”, “where’s the super market close to my hostel?”</li>
</ol>
<p>Once you finished the mitigation step, we would need to find out the root cause of the problems. And usually you would be stucked at these steps and you have no idea how to make a breakthrough.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>The sequence of outcomes doesn’t match what you’ve expected, which frustrated you.</li>
<li>You lost motivation, and not sure what’s the meaning of doing certain things though you could find some weak reasons.</li>
<li>The constraints are too many and you’re not able to solve them all.</li>
</ol>
<p>Before jumping into the detail, I’d like to address what’s the foundation / framework on tackling these problem. It’s the logic system borrowed from Philosophy and Mathematics. Like dealing with any problem in life you must admit a foundation where you could build solid ground on. To me it is the logic rules and axiom, even the modern theology is built on logic and axiom. I don’t see any better foundation you could rely upon at this moment. The difference and the key part is to know yourself well, since that would play a key role to know what your axiom are. For example: Your personality is like Alex Honnold in the documentary film: Free Solo where you have a big heart for adventure. You can’t tell why since that’s a part of yourself. It is what it is and you can’t ask further, that’s your axiom and it would be the starting point for reasoning in your logic system. It would be another story if your personality is conservative on risk. When facing on the same type of scenario, the same logic rules with different axiom could lead to very different reasonable action items. They are true respectively in their own logic system. Understanding this fact would aslo help you whether to take advice from others. Their advice could be very helpful in their own background but may not apply that well in your system.</p>
<p>Apart from the logic system mentioned above, I also borrowed probabilistic thinking from the master poker players and investing guru. If you read enough you’d notice that the probablistic thinking they are not only applied well in those domains. Your daily life are challenged by a lot of uncertainty and unsure, where they are subject to certain known or unknown distribution. But people rarely see it that way, they would see they did something wrong when the outcome was not right. It might be true, but you have to take a grain of sale on that where you need to guess what’s the oracle distribution behind the world you’re facing and you still might face bad outcome with certain probability even you are doing the right thing. It might just you’re just unlucky for the time being. And the reasonable action is to keep doing it until it reverses to the mean.</p>
<p>Beyond that, sometimes the feedback loop are unnoticeable in incremental amount. The typical tasks like these are language learning and gym training. You have to sort of “believe” that eventually it would work out and stick with it for a time window until you make it. You have to be able to identify the difficulties you are facing is just a part of that kind.</p>
<p>With the above said, now we could tackle the three scenarios mentioned above to find out the root cause.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Make sure if you are just unlucky for this sequence of bad outcomes, is it significant enough to make you question maybe your view on the oracle distribution might be wrong, if it is then change your view, and start with a new distribution hypothesis and change your action accordingly. Then test them out with your future efforts. The world is not fixed in stone and keep changing, so the oracle distribution might over changes over time, it is called non-strationary distribution in Mathematics</li>
<li>If you start to question what the meaning of working on taks A. Usually you’re asking the wrong question. You would never asked yourself what the meaning is to have Hamburger for dinner if you’re up to it, since your body feel like it. That means your axiom mismatches with what you thought you are. You start to cheat on yourself’s feeling. The correct question is, how should I follow my body tells me but at the same time I could make enough of money, support myself etc. That’s the constraints put by reality. Wasting time on finding the meaning is looking for the solutions in the wrong direction.</li>
<li>If you’ve ever felt too many constraints in life: Like you are married and have two kids, and you still feel like you’d like to climb the corporate ladder and make good progress in your career. It’s like the tasks you faced in corporate life, make a priority and drop some of the contraints. People tend to have more in life but not aware that more values in life usually they would conflict with each others in unexpected ways, or resource contention. Even for very generalized concepts like democracy and freedom could result into dark corners where you have to make a trade-off. Once you re-examine the contraints, and re-examine your logic rules in your system. You could probably find a way to work-around the “bug”. It’s pretty much debugging software products, where you could leverage on debugging skill by removing certain constraints and see if the output would change if not subjecting to heisenbug.</li>
</ol>
<p>Usually you would know the action items once you identify the root cause. Sometimes it is not that easy. However, the world is big, I would like to lay my belief not on deity but the fact that the world is big and believing that the difficulty you face today might have been resolved by somebody else in the world before. Read more blog posts and books to learn from others’ expereience. Especially the brighter ones. I like Bill Gates’ method to reset, where he would bring tens of books and lock himself into an isolated woodhouse in the forest and focus himself on the topic. I also tried this method by myself. I read the tens of books from business people, or the topics that I wouldn’t usually touch to explore the inspiration from others. And they might share the misearble situation they faced before and when realizing those, you would feel you are in a much better position. It would do good on seal healing the wound. This method create positive optionality. Traveling to challenging place would sort of play the same type of roles, but mostly distraction since those wouldn’t bring knowledge from reading a book.</p>
<p>Again, these are the framework I adopted, and I assume the methodology would only apply to certain group of audience. I kind of abstract the process how people self cure the mental problems over the years and come up with this framework. I don’t know how far it could apply but it works well for myself and a few samples around me. Hope that is helpful.</p>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>New Start in Toronto</title>
    <link href="https://blog.paulme.ng/posts/2020-02-17-new-start-in-toronto.html" />
    <id>https://blog.paulme.ng/posts/2020-02-17-new-start-in-toronto.html</id>
    <published>2020-02-17T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2020-02-17T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/2020-02-17/IMG_4519.jpeg" /><br />
<img src="/images/2020-02-17/IMG_4528.jpeg" /><br />
<img src="/images/2020-02-17/IMG_4537.jpeg" /><br />
<img src="/images/2020-02-17/IMG_4552.jpeg" /><br />
<img src="/images/2020-02-17/IMG_4592.jpeg" /></p>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>The End of 2019</title>
    <link href="https://blog.paulme.ng/posts/2020-01-01-the-end-of-2019.html" />
    <id>https://blog.paulme.ng/posts/2020-01-01-the-end-of-2019.html</id>
    <published>2020-01-01T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2020-01-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is the last day of 2019, it was transformative year. I’ve learned a lot by practicing. I faced challenges and learned to make difficult decisions but make the decision rationally. When I faced challenges I like to do binge reading, part of the reasons is that I have the presumption that there must be smart people have been through the challenges I faced today. When I watched the documentary “Inside Bill’s Brain” I noticed that he also has the binge reading habit. He would lock himself in a room and read everything he can about a topic. The books I have finished in the past several weeks are:</p>
<ul>
<li>The man who solved the market</li>
<li>A Man of All Markets</li>
<li>Dear Chairman</li>
<li>Quench your own Thirst</li>
<li>The Ride of a Lifetime</li>
<li>Never Split the difference</li>
<li>My Father’s Business</li>
<li>公司的品格 2</li>
<li>一人の力で日経平均を動かせる男の投資哲学</li>
<li>尋找夢想的家</li>
<li>監工完全上手事件書</li>
</ul>
<p>I’ve learned to like Audiobooks and I would say it really help a lot on your reading efficiency since it would make you effectively use your time on the road or while you are jogging. This easily adds another hour or two on each of the day. It could also let your eyes to rest, especially for a software engineer where you already use your eyes a lot. I can simply borrow the Audiobook from Singapore library and finish it in one week or two (The deadline of borrowing a book also creates urgency so that you feel like finishing it).</p>
<p>最後、2020年で日本語が上手になりたいです。練習のため、このブログでもとも日本語の文を書きます。真剣に日本語を勉強したい動機は日本の株式の情報収集です。決算報告の日本語分かったら、それが私の競争上の優位性です。後、勉強の仕方を教えます。</p>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Linux materials I read in the past few weeks</title>
    <link href="https://blog.paulme.ng/posts/2019-12-29-linux-materials-in-the-past-few-weeks.html" />
    <id>https://blog.paulme.ng/posts/2019-12-29-linux-materials-in-the-past-few-weeks.html</id>
    <published>2019-12-29T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2019-12-29T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve been watching videos and books to get myself familiar with eBPF tooling, more toward Linux network stack and VFS. This post serves as a note on what I’ve learned.</p>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/bj3qdEDbCD4" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen>
</iframe>
<p>Brendan Gregg has listed the command line tools that are useful for analyzing a Linux instance if he has to ssh into the instance. They could be preliminary analysis to quickly get a feel on what’s going on on a specific instance.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>uptime</li>
<li>dmesg -T | tail</li>
<li>vmstat 1</li>
<li>mpstat -P ALL 1</li>
<li>pidstat 1</li>
<li>iostat -xz 1</li>
<li>free -m</li>
<li>sar -n DEV 1</li>
<li>sar -n TCP,ETCP 1</li>
<li>top</li>
</ol>
<p>To dig deeper into the detail, these eBPF-based tooling would be helpful.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>execsnoop</li>
<li>opensnoop</li>
<li>ext4slower</li>
<li>biolatency</li>
<li>biosnoop</li>
<li>cachestat</li>
<li>tcpconnect</li>
<li>tcpaccept</li>
<li>tcpretrans</li>
<li>gethostlatency</li>
<li>runqlat</li>
<li>profile</li>
</ol>
<p>When the information you are trying to get are not there, and <code>strace</code> is not enough. The following tools could be helpful to peek into the critical paths in the kernel modules.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>trace</li>
<li>argdist</li>
</ol>
<p>A nice book to read is a <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Performance-Tools-Addison-Wesley-Professional-Computing-ebook-dp-B081ZDXNL3/dp/B081ZDXNL3">new book</a> authored by Brendan.</p>
<p>While studying for the SRE materials, I also found Cloudflare has many good blog posts that I could learn from.</p>
<p>A blog post on how to optimize for <a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/http-2-prioritization-with-nginx/">http2</a> stack gives really good insight on how the Linux network stack works.</p>
<pre><code>net.core.default_qdisc = fq
net.ipv4.tcp_congestion_control = bbr
net.ipv4.tcp_notsent_lowat = 16384</code></pre>
<p>Their interview questions also makes you start to question yourself if you really know the modern TCP/IP stack.</p>
<pre><code>Archaeology

    What is the lowest TCP port number?

    The TCP frame has an URG pointer field, when is it used?

    Can the RST packet have a payload?

    When is the &quot;flow&quot; field in IPv6 used?

    What does the IP_FREEBIND socket option do?

Forgotten Quirks

    What does the PSH flag actually do?

    The TCP timestamp is implicated in SYN cookies. How?

    Can a &quot;UDP&quot; packet have a checksum field set to zero?

    How does TCP simultaneous open work? Does it actually work?

Fragmentation and Congestion

    What is a stupid window syndrome?

    What are the CWE and ECE flags in TCP header?

    What is the IP ID field and what does it have to do with DF bit? Why do some packets have a non-zero IP ID and a DF set?

Fresh Ideas

    Can a SYN packet have a payload? (hint: new RFC proposals)

    Can a SYN+ACK packet have a payload?

ICMP Path MTU

    ICMP packet-too-big messages are returned by routers and contain a part of the original packet in the payload. What is the minimal length of this payload that is accepted by Linux?

    When an ICMP packet-too-big message is returned by an intermediate router it will have the source IP of that router. In practice though, we often see a source IP of the ICMP message to be identical to the destination IP of the original packet. Why could that happen?

Linux Configuration

    Linux has a &quot;tcp_no_metrics_save&quot; sysctl setting. What does it save and for how long?

    Linux uses two queues to handle incoming TCP connections: the SYN queue and the accept queue. What is the length of the SYN queue?

    What happens if the SYN queue grows too large and overflows?

Touching the router

    What are BGP bogons, and why are they less of a problem now?

    TCP has an extension which adds MD5 checksums to packets. When is it useful?

And finally:

    What are the differences in checksumming algorithms in IPv4 and IPv6?</code></pre>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Global Deep Value Strategy</title>
    <link href="https://blog.paulme.ng/posts/2019-11-19-global-deep-value-strategy.html" />
    <id>https://blog.paulme.ng/posts/2019-11-19-global-deep-value-strategy.html</id>
    <published>2019-11-19T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2019-11-19T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I noticed an introduction on xueqiue about <a href="https://www.cambriafunds.com/gval">GVAL</a> ETF the other day. I got intrigued by its strategy and had a look. Its issued Cambria is run by Meb Faber, who runs the podcast on iTunes and quite well-known among investors. I watched his interview with Ed Thorp before. It is a good one.</p>
<p>Roughly speaking the fund’s strategy is to value the countries or regions by Shiller 10 year CAPE ratio and pick the bottom 25% as the universe, and then select the top 30 stocks by the market cap and filter them further by traditional P/E, P/B, P/FCF, EV/EBITDA etc. The final picks are about 100 stocks and rebalance the portfolio every year. For the detail, you could check the <a href="https://www.cambriafunds.com/Data/Sites/30/media/docs/GVAL_Methodology.pdf">prospectus</a></p>
<p>And the pie chart for the regions and countries like this. <img src="/images/2019-11-19/by_region.png" /> <img src="/images/2019-11-19/by_country.png" /></p>
<p>Since fund’s introduction mentioned Graham and Dodds. I couldn’t help to link that with Graham’s net-net strategy, to use a bag of extremely low value to bet it statistically would “somehow” reverse to the mean. I know Graham in general encourage to hold it for 3 years, if nothing happen then sell it. However, seeing the fund’s underperformance in the last two years, I couldn’t help to list a few of the reasons that may not happen.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Country suffers longer than individual company from the structural reason. You could insert new management or somehow an earning quarter activate the hidden value. But country’s policy move slower. New bill need to be passed, and cabinet need to be formed in any of democratic regimes.</li>
<li>Comparing to the companies in the same currency zone, the international flow of the money is decided by too many factors. If the money not flowing in those countries then the value wouldn’t recover. There has to be some reason to flow in, and merely undervalue may not be a strong enough reason.</li>
</ol>
<p>I tried to make another list by the <a href="http://pages.stern.nyu.edu/~adamodar/New_Home_Page/datacurrent.html">data</a> compiled by Damodaran. I removed the countries that has too few stocks listed, and sorted the list by from high to low by ROIC, then ROE. and low to high by EV/EBIT. The reason to make this sorting is that I think marginal investment return would be a stronger reason to attract the money to flow in, but not simply low value. The list is like the following:</p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>country</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Thailand</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Finland</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>China</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Singapore</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Denmark</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Japan</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Hong Kong</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>South Africa</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Taiwan</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Bangladesh</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Vietnam</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>United Arab Emirates</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Argentina</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Italy</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Nigeria</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Jordan</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Netherlands</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Russia</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Mexico</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Switzerland</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Romania</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Turkey</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Sri Lanka</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Egypt</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Oman</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>For the top 20 there are some overlaps, but the rankings that was in the low Shiller 10 year CAPE are ranked lower. This ranking somehow matches with some of my private findings of good value company globally. I would argue this ranking should be a relative good pool to fish. But not the simply low multiple ranking. With that said, I didn’t do thorough research to do back-testing etc. It’s simply my hunch though.</p>
<p>This is just a rundown of my thoughts, not a rigorous research.</p>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>The Man Who Solved The Market</title>
    <link href="https://blog.paulme.ng/posts/2019-11-18-the-man-who-solved-the-market.html" />
    <id>https://blog.paulme.ng/posts/2019-11-18-the-man-who-solved-the-market.html</id>
    <published>2019-11-18T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2019-11-18T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>To me this is the book of the year 2019.</p>
<p>I can barely recall when was the first time I heard about the name of Renaissance Technologies. It is probably back in 2010 when I got intrigued by the world of Quant and I was reading Derman’s book: My life as a Quant. I googled a little bit of the development of the financial modeling and tried to know the landscape of the hedge funds that are quantitative funds. It didn’t take too long to run into the name of Jim Simons. As a STEM student growing up in Asia, his associate with Shiing-shen Chern and Chern–Simons theory immediately brought my attention. By further digging up the techniques adopted by Renaissance Technologies. The names of Peter Brown and Robert Mercer came up, they are the students of Frederick Jelinek, a figure you must know if you were in my topic of research: Speech Recognition. The rumor that they were using Hidden Markov Model at the time of early 90s excited me, where HMM was the model you could not skip in my field. Most of the research was trying to build adds-on to the core HMM infrastructure.</p>
<p>This book isn’t about to tell you about the skills adopted by Renaissance Technmologies, but a biography of Jim Simons by Gregory Zuckerman. Renaissance Technologies has stayed low-key for a long time and their secretive style makes few people know the history of the fund. Gregory did a good job to piece together the history, the challenges and the crisis where Jim has faced, and key figures helped establish the foundation of the company. It shed more humanity colors to the stereotype that a group of mathematicians and scientists should be run the company rationally and pursue the path of philosopher king as described by Plato. However, it is far from what was happening in the fund. Drama and crisis was no different from other companies.</p>
<p>The book is so much fun to read and I would like to put down a few notes and thoughts in bullet points.</p>
<ul>
<li>It sounds to me the most important thing to quantitative fund is cost estimation with control and risk management, unlike the most of the people intuitively think it is the precision of the prediction. It reads like Renaissance Technologies have its moat because its early setback so Simons was more risk-aware than others like LTCM, so they are less susceptible to the tail risk.</li>
<li>On the cost end, apart from hiring the talents to discover signals, a new breed of quantitative fund like World Quant is to shift the cost of the mathematicians and scientist to Asia, where they only need to pay half of the salary than in the USA, which reduce the expense ratio for a fund to succeed. It sounds so much like running a bank where the metric is to check the expense rate.</li>
<li>The early pioneers of the quant is more connected than I thought, Kelly’s criterion was known and was applied by Berlekamp to their trading models.</li>
<li>They also look for the statistically significant signals that don’t necessarily obvious in its logical cause, which is a surprise to me. But it seems that it made them a moat since they have a scaling bet strategy that could safely try it out and shrink it back if the signal fade away.</li>
<li>Ed Thorp was almost to invest in Renaissance Technology, but he decided not to when he found Jim was a chain smoker.</li>
<li>Statistical Arbitrage, though so obvious on the paper, there are so many details to take care to put into the practice it seems.</li>
<li>George Soros and Jim Simons are neighbors. In the congress hearing during the financial crisis, you could see that Soros and Jim were sitting together in the picture. It seems that Jim agrees with the worldview of Soros. In the epilogue, a MIT student asked Jim which investor’s advice they should listen to on the path of learning investment. Jim pondered and replied George Soros. The same answer was given by Nassim Taleb.</li>
</ul>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>新加坡住宅房地產的粗略研究</title>
    <link href="https://blog.paulme.ng/posts/2019-10-27-%E6%96%B0%E5%8A%A0%E5%9D%A1%E4%BD%8F%E5%AE%85%E6%88%BF%E5%9C%B0%E7%94%A2%E7%9A%84%E7%B2%97%E7%95%A5%E7%A0%94%E7%A9%B6.html" />
    <id>https://blog.paulme.ng/posts/2019-10-27-%E6%96%B0%E5%8A%A0%E5%9D%A1%E4%BD%8F%E5%AE%85%E6%88%BF%E5%9C%B0%E7%94%A2%E7%9A%84%E7%B2%97%E7%95%A5%E7%A0%94%E7%A9%B6.html</id>
    <published>2019-10-27T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2019-10-27T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>由於最近被詢問這個問題，所以花了一點時間研究一下，大致是用三個樣本來粗估計算對於外國人能買的 Condomium 的 Cap Rate，算是當作只賭出租計算而不賭增值的保守估計。</p>
<p>首先我定義我的 Cap Rate After Tax 如下</p>
<pre><code>(Net Operating Income - Tax) / Current Market Value</code></pre>
<p>我把稅務還有維護費用成本加進來，但沒有算進折舊，就股票來比較的話比較像是 NOPAT 吧。Top Line 的部分假設沒有任何一個閒置的月份，是最理想的情況。</p>
<p>挑的三個樣本有</p>
<ul>
<li>Rosalia Park</li>
<li>Kovan Regency</li>
<li>Casa Cambio</li>
</ul>
<p>他們大概都是位在離市中心搭地鐵 30-40 分鐘的地方，在新加坡東北邊，屬於比較早期發展的區域。周邊生活機能還算不錯，有大的 shopping mall 也有 hawker Center。硬是要類比台北的話，可能有點像新店吧。這邊都用公開能夠找到的資料，Property Guru 有點像是信義房屋或是 Redfin。</p>
<h2 id="rosalia-park">Rosalia Park</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.propertyguru.com.sg/listing/21756729/for-sale-rosalia-park">For Sale</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.propertyguru.com.sg/listing/22056526/for-rent-rosalia-park">For Rent</a></li>
</ul>
<table>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th style="text-align: left;">Item</th>
<th style="text-align: left;">Price</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">Rent Income</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">33600</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">Property Tax</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">(3423)</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">Cando Fee + Utility</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">(3600)</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">Maintenance</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">(1000)</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">Home Insurance</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">(200)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th style="text-align: left;">Calculation</th>
<th style="text-align: left;">Rate</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">Rental Yield</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">1.816%</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">Cap Rate</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">1.371%</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>網站上寫了 Rental Yield Estimated: 2.37% - 2.71%，但自己計算是遠低於那個。我猜網站是照 2016 年的交易價格算的。那時候的成交價是 1.3M SGD。</p>
<p>1.8% 的 Rental Yield 有夠爛。US 10 year Treasury 都有 1.7% 左右，而且幾乎無風險。當然房子的好處是會隨通膨而漲價。估計如果自己改裝 layout 成出租隔間的話，總租金可以收到 4000 SGD。那 Cap Rate 可以到 2.15%，這樣會比較好一些，不過自己管理的時間成本也高了很多。</p>
<h2 id="kovan-regency">Kovan Regency</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.propertyguru.com.sg/listing/22047260/for-sale-kovan-regency">For Sale</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.propertyguru.com.sg/listing/19601048/for-rent-kovan-regency">For Rent</a></li>
</ul>
<table>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th style="text-align: left;">Item</th>
<th style="text-align: left;">Price</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">Rent Income</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">43200</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">Property Tax.</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">(4584)</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">Cando Fee + Utility</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">(3600)</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">Maintenance</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">(1000)</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">Home Insurance</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">(200)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th style="text-align: left;">Calculation</th>
<th style="text-align: left;">Rate</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">Rental Yield</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">2.618%</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">Cap Rate</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">2.05%</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>網站上的 Rental Yield Estimated 是 2.5% - 3.17%，還是高估不過比較接近了。</p>
<h2 id="casa-cambio">Casa Cambio</h2>
<p>這一棟比較小戶型，比較類似 Studio</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.propertyguru.com.sg/listing/21981592/for-rent-casa-cambio">For Rent</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.propertyguru.com.sg/listing/20771858/for-sale-casa-cambio">For Sale</a></li>
</ul>
<table>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th style="text-align: left;">Item</th>
<th style="text-align: left;">Price</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">Rent Income</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">30600</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">Property Tax.</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">(3072)</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">Cando Fee + Utility</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">(2400)</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">Maintenance</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">(1000)</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">Home Insurance</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">(200)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th style="text-align: left;">Calculation</th>
<th style="text-align: left;">Rate</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">Rental Yield</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">2.49%</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">Cap Rate</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">1.945%</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>所以稍微小的戶型也並沒有比較好。</p>
<h2 id="其他一些市場的細節">其他一些市場的細節</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li>交易買家需要付印花稅，是累進稅率，不過對於外國人大概 2.8-3%</li>
<li>對於外國人很多要付額外的印花稅來防止炒房，大概是另外 20%，美國人不用。</li>
<li>根據 PR 跟 Citizen，第一套房或第二套房不同，付的額外印花稅從 0-15% 不等</li>
<li>每年 Property Tax 是用假設你出租的收入來算，假如你真的出租的話又是另一套稅率，會比較高一些。</li>
</ol>
<p>可以參考這兩篇</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.propertyguru.com.sg/property-guides/step-by-step-guide-for-buying-property-in-singapore-as-a-foreigner-12304">Step-by-step guide for buying property in Singapore as a foreigner</a></li>
<li><a href="https://blog.moneysmart.sg/property/investing-singapore-property/">Investing in Property in Singapore – Singapore Property Tax &amp; Buying Guide</a></li>
</ul>
<p>而 Tax 的部分比較複雜</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.iras.gov.sg/IRASHome/Property/Property-owners/Learning-the-basics/About-Annual-Value/">IRAS 的 Property Tax 官方資料</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.iras.gov.sg/IRASHome/Other-Taxes/Stamp-Duty-for-Property/Working-out-your-Stamp-Duty/Buying-or-Acquiring-Property/What-is-the-Duty-that-I-Need-to-Pay-as-a-Buyer-or-Transferee-of-Residential-Property/Buyer-s-Stamp-Duty--BSD-/">IRAS 的 Stamp Duty 官方資料</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.iras.gov.sg/IRASHome/Other-Taxes/Stamp-Duty-for-Property/Working-out-your-Stamp-Duty/Buying-or-Acquiring-Property/What-is-the-Duty-that-I-Need-to-Pay-as-a-Buyer-or-Transferee-of-Residential-Property/Additional-Buyer-s-Stamp-Duty--ABSD-/">IRAS 的 Additional Buyer Stamp Duty 官方資料</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.sgmoneymatters.com/property-tax-singapore/">How to calculate your property tax in Singapore</a></li>
</ul>
<p>而 Condo 的話有區分是 Free-hold，租期 99 年或 999 年，細節可以看這兩篇</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.propertyguru.com.sg/property-guides/what-are-the-options-for-a-leasehold-property-owners-when-their-99-years-tenure-is-about-to-end-10106">What are the Options for a Leasehold Property Owners when their 99 years Tenure is about to End?</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.99.co/blog/singapore/freehold-vs-leasehold-condos/">Freehold vs leasehold condos – Which is the best choice? There are pros and cons to buying a freehold vs a leasehold condo</a></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="總體資料">總體資料</h2>
<p>政府每一季會發<a href="https://www.ura.gov.sg/Corporate/Media-Room/Media-Releases/pr19-32">報告</a>。根據政府編制的房地產指數，過去 Private properties 的走勢<a href="https://data.gov.sg/dataset/private-residential-property-price-index-by-type-of-property">如這裡</a>，從前面的低點又回來一些。不過要注意一個細節，他的所謂 private properties 包含了 shop, office, user factory and warehouse。我沒有找到只包含住宅的指數。如果是 HDB 的話，走勢可以從<a href="https://data.gov.sg/dataset/hdb-resale-price-index">這裡</a>看到，可以看出來是不斷走低的。</p>
<p>另外 HDB也有公布租金價格中位數跟價格中位數。我擷取了其中一個地區。簡單計算一下 Rental Yield 高了很多，可以到 7.5%，HDB 的話還不用付 Condo Fee，所以粗估 Cap Rate 可能有 7%</p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th style="text-align: left;">Time</th>
<th style="text-align: left;">Location</th>
<th>Type</th>
<th style="text-align: left;">Price</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">2019-Q2</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">ANG MO KIO</td>
<td>3RM</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">1700</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">2019-Q2</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">ANG MO KIO</td>
<td>4RM</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">2100</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">2019-Q2</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">ANG MO KIO</td>
<td>5RM</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">2300</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<table>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th style="text-align: left;">Time</th>
<th style="text-align: left;">Location</th>
<th>Type</th>
<th style="text-align: left;">Price</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">2019-Q2</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">ANG MO KIO</td>
<td>3RM</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">272000</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td style="text-align: left;">2019-Q2</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">ANG MO KIO</td>
<td>4RM</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">412500</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td style="text-align: left;">2019-Q2</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">ANG MO KIO</td>
<td>5RM</td>
<td style="text-align: left;">680000</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://data.gov.sg/dataset/median-resale-prices-for-registered-applications-by-town-and-flat-type">HDB 的 resale price</a></li>
<li><a href="https://data.gov.sg/dataset/median-rent-by-town-and-flat-type">HDB 的租金</a></li>
</ul>
<p>不過 HDB 並不是一個自由的市場，要出租的規定也很多。一手的只有公民可以買。要買二手的話至少也要 PR，對於沒有結婚的 PR 還只能買其中一種比較貴的，結婚的話才能買其他種。對於收入超過一定的也沒辦法買 HDB，所以新加坡年輕人結婚的話也早，因為要買租屋的話等到收入高了就只能買 Condo。</p>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>最近讀的一些投資方面的讀物</title>
    <link href="https://blog.paulme.ng/posts/2019-10-20-%E6%9C%80%E8%BF%91%E8%AE%80%E7%9A%84%E4%B8%80%E4%BA%9B%E6%8A%95%E8%B3%87%E6%96%B9%E9%9D%A2%E7%9A%84%E8%AE%80%E7%89%A9.html" />
    <id>https://blog.paulme.ng/posts/2019-10-20-%E6%9C%80%E8%BF%91%E8%AE%80%E7%9A%84%E4%B8%80%E4%BA%9B%E6%8A%95%E8%B3%87%E6%96%B9%E9%9D%A2%E7%9A%84%E8%AE%80%E7%89%A9.html</id>
    <published>2019-10-20T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2019-10-20T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>讀得有點雜，不過論文方面讀到比較深刻的就是</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Investing in the Unknown and Unknowable</li>
</ol>
<p>作者是 Larry Summers 的老師，自己本身也是投資人，基本上是一篇他對於投資的一些觀察，成功的人基本上都是在處理 Unknown 跟 Unknowable 情況計算良好並控制好風險的人，然後只要有正向的高倍率的 Optionality 發生，就能賺到許多錢。在投資的許多場合，機率這個思考框架根本是沒有用的，試想要如何評估將來二十年內自動車大量普及的情況的機率是多少，或是另外一個 911 發生的機率是多少，幾乎是不可能的。而且還有大量黑天鵝事件。所以要根據每個個別情況衡量是否有不對稱性可以利用。然後在能夠辨別跟跟隨領域菁英的時候也不用羞於抄襲別人的投資。</p>
<p>至於給投資人的信主要就是從下面幾個投資人開始讀，不過太長了還沒讀完。我特別喜歡 Michael Burry 因為他也是從 Nobody 開始，比較有參考性。而 Ben Graham 還有 Walter Scholoss 的體系因為分散的關係比較不會害人。Warren Buffet 是有很多智慧但越深入了解就覺得他把一些沒那麼輕鬆的事講得有點輕鬆。不清楚的人會被害到。</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Warren Buffet 合夥人時期</li>
<li>Ben Graham</li>
<li>Michael Burry</li>
<li>Walter Schloss</li>
<li>Brookfield</li>
</ol>
<p>另外也聽了知名量化基金 AQR 有一個 podcast 的訪談。就是量化跟人腦到底誰的績效整體比較好。結論是沒有什麼差別。但量化是贏在系統穩定，穩定的小贏累積出來。而人腦就是靠打中全壘打。量化的好處也是比較沒有人腦情緒的干擾。但同時一個重要的點是要在你的系統出問題的時候你能夠知道到底是暫時不 work，還是說你的系統失效了。Ed Thorp 在訪談中有說過，你必須事先定義你系統的容錯率，如果你出現了意外的大賺跟大虧損都要反省你的系統是不是有問題。</p>
<p>我覺得 Seeking Alpha 上 Ruerd Heeg 定義的四種策略是不錯的，也是 Ben Graham / Joel Greenblatt 那種人腦跟簡易量化混合的方式，</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Qualitative Microcap</li>
<li>Low EV/EBIT, EV/EBITDA</li>
<li>Net-net</li>
<li>Falling knife</li>
</ol>
<p>在長期來講，最好的還是雪球股，也就是 Qualitative Microcap。在他還小還沒被發現的時候買進他，為什麼要從小的挑是因為，流動性高的已經有太多機構參與，人家每天在看是看不贏別人的，Microcap 太小大資金的是看不上的，而且美國有規定股價太低的話機構沒辦法投資，是一個老舊的法規幫助機構的手腳，而一般散戶也不會注意到 Microcap。雪球股難的地方是你需要在你的領域超強，看出別人看不出的細節跟未來。要不然你就是要去超冷門的地方做。並且需要時間去累積，一直讀資料等等，所以這是長期的目標。短期內先盡量比較容易看懂的或是軟體產業。</p>
<p>而 2,3,4 都是比較偏量化的策略，是有研究論文支持的，如果能在全球法規足夠完善的地方去分散小部位，統計上來講應該是勝率夠高的。用量化的好處是不會做出太笨的事，然後也不會花太多時間，screener 篩出來後還是會看一下 corporate governance 這塊，如果沒太大問題就可以考慮。這樣我人腦的部分只要先練習出比人家更能看出 corporate governance 的問題就能贏過市場上大部分人，而 corporate governance 這一塊也是機構的機器人還無法量化的部分，所以暫時不會被機器人打敗。越涉及到 Unknown and Unknowable 的部分就越不會被量化策略基金威脅到。</p>
<p>當我閱讀越多的感想，我越覺得除了少數的例外，成功的投資人都是成功的生意人。其實投資也是在拚生意的眼光，就算是做房地產，我知道有一派的投資客也是靠老屋翻修，或是翻修成社區型住宿來賺取比較高的報酬，畢竟房地產也是有他的邏輯，不可能永遠無腦資金行情上漲。我看到賺的好的幾乎都不是純的投金錢而已，都是由翻修等動作的經營本質。而股票中 Activist 的行動也是類似，採取經營權把不適合的管理層換掉來解放價值，甚至像是 Carl Icahn 就有養自己專門的團隊在拿下企業後去整頓。而巴菲特用保險公司去投資 Float，也只是把保險公司的本質做到最完善，很多人想要仿照買了保險公司想如法炮製但卻失敗，因為管不好保險公司。新一代的人我有看到不用保險公司而用 Domain Name 註冊公司，也就是 SaaS 公司來達到同樣的目的，也是先收錢在辦事，但比起經營保險公司簡單很多，是蠻聰明的做法。</p>
<p>希望有毅力定期寫讀物心得..</p>
]]></summary>
</entry>
<entry>
    <title>Kelly Criterion 與 Portfolio Management 的思考</title>
    <link href="https://blog.paulme.ng/posts/2019-10-19-kelly-criterion-%E8%88%87-portfolio-management-%E7%9A%84%E6%80%9D%E8%80%83.html" />
    <id>https://blog.paulme.ng/posts/2019-10-19-kelly-criterion-%E8%88%87-portfolio-management-%E7%9A%84%E6%80%9D%E8%80%83.html</id>
    <published>2019-10-19T00:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2019-10-19T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p>最近一直對 Portfolio Management 方面還有看事情角度有蠻多疑問，看了一些投資機構的文章以及去爬知名投資人的寫作，最終的結論還是要看每個人的個性。不過從一些從 Kelly Criterion 角度出發的<a href="https://intrinsicinvesting.com/2019/09/03/position-sizing-why-conviction-matters/">文章</a>還是多少有些幫助的。這篇把看過的一些東西記錄下來。</p>
<p>Kelly Criterion 是被 Monish Pabrai 寫進書裡才比較出名，很多知名投資人都有用。最初也是 Ed Thorp，一個戰勝賭場的 MIT 教授發揚光大的。主要是用在賭場中，但他用在投資裡面有缺陷，主要因為</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>投資許多情況下機率的事件分佈無法衡量</li>
<li>回報也是未知數，並不見得是贏了是固定的倍數</li>
</ol>
<p>所以現實中多辦用到 1/4 Kelly 就已經很多了。甚至有變形，使用最多願意輸的錢 * Kelly 算出來的比例。</p>
<p>而減小 Kelly 的倍數而不要下過大的賭注是因為整個市場（不只股市）有厚尾跟黑天鵝的特性。有一些投資人就是專門做黑天鵝的，像是 Anti-Fragile 的作者 Nassim Taleb 他之前就有一個基金是做 Options 來賭黑天鵝，他也是這麼發家的。另一個算是做黑天鵝的是索羅斯，而且他又是賭特別難以捉摸的總體經濟部分，他也有對於世界運作的一套反身性哲學。他們的系統都太難學了，運作的方式也是要大資金一般人根本沒辦法複製。</p>
<p>有一個容易忽略掉的一點就是漏看了細節。儘管巴菲特跟他風格的投資人如果是非常確定的時候會下大注，但一個關鍵點就是他們下大注常常其實也是為了拿到董事會的席位，獲得內線跟投票權，甚至是決定權。這樣其實是更安全的，因為你找到機會後可以然公司照你的方向改變，而不是希望公司的管理層聽你的建議而已。這是我這次在一篇一篇看巴菲特早年合夥人時代的信發現的。他的 Sanborn Map Corp. 就是這樣操作。而對於資金量沒有辦法買到董事席位的投資人，就算你是搭其他 Activist Investor 的順風車，你也應該要不要賭過大的部位因為你沒有董事會投票權，你的生存是操在別人手上。並且加入一些技術分析的手段來保障不可知的情況，像是別人有內線在市場上倒貨。我以前對技術分析覺得不合時宜，因為</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>現在都是機器人量化了，技術指標那些在北美市場早就被套利完了，幾乎是不太可能有用</li>
<li>對於流動性股票強的股票也因為關注過多，資訊很快就會反應。不做毫秒級根本沒有意義。但那些 high frequency trading 的機構都已經做完了。</li>
</ol>
<p>這次看到 Michael Burry 早年在 MSN 的文章，我還蠻驚訝他居然會用簡單的技術分析當作進入點還有加入停損。他說是因為 practical reasons，主要是避免 fundamental 分析的缺陷還有自己可能的錯誤，在他用了簡單的 trading 規則加上停損規則之後，他的 portfolio 沒有因為單一部位爆炸而爆炸過。所以可以推測在超早期他曾經也因為單一部位爆炸而讓整個 portfolio 炸過。只有對於像是 Asset play 還有雪球股他說不會停損。對於他的說法我覺得很合理。</p>
<p>而 Monish Pabrai 的作法就是儘管再看好也只會下 10%，不過我之前看到他 AER 的部位都 40% 了，但那應該是漲上去的結果，另一方面也是他並不是所有部位都在美國，我們並不知道他美國以外部位的大小。所以他的做法其實比較像是最多願意輸的錢 * Kelly 算出來的比例。</p>
<p>有想到更多的話再更新..</p>
]]></summary>
</entry>

</feed>
